Guide to the August Claessens Papers TAM 021 (R-7124/56)
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
August Claessens Papers
1911-1955
TAM 021 (R-7124/56)
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
2.25 Linear feet (5 boxes)
August Claessens was a leading educational and political figure in the Socialist Party. In the fall of 1917, Claessens was elected to the New York State Assembly, as a representative of one of Manhattan's Lower East Side assembly districts, and was one of five socialist assemblymen who the Assembly refused to seat after their 1919 reelections. In 1922 Claessens was allowed to take office after being re-elected for the third time. In the mid-1930s Claessens withdrew from the Socialist Party and became the executive secretary and, later, the national chairman of the Social Democratic Federation. Claessens held the position of national chairman until his death in 1954, and also ran unsuccessfully for a number of local and state offices. Claessens taught a variety of subjects at the Rand School of Social Science from the mid-1920s until his death in 1954, including public speaking, psychology, race relations, labor-management relations, socialist theory, politics, anthropology, and sex and society. Claessens also served as an instructor in several evening schools sponsored by various New York City labor unions. The collection contains manuscripts, lecture notes, correspondence, clippings and ephemera. NOTE: the collecction is microfilmed, and researchers must use the microfilm copy (R-7124, reel 56).
Claessens, August, 1885-1954.
Box 1-5
Provenance
Transferred from the Rand School Archives, 1962.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions, however, patrons must use microfilm (R-7124, reel 56).
Historical/Biographical Note
August Claessens was one of the most influential leaders in the educational and political development of the Socialist Party. Shortly after becoming a socialist in 1909, Claessens helped organize support for the Socialist Party within several New York City labor unions. in the fall of 1917, Claessens was elected to the New York State Assembly. As a representative of one of the Lower Manhattan assembly districts, Claessens drafted and worked for legislation pertaining to child labor, the penal code's procedures for obtaining an admission of quilt, the abolishment of the Volstead Act, the abolishment of the death penalty, and the regulation of police powers in suppressing strikes. on 1 April 1920, Claessens was one of five socialist assemblymen who were expelled from the State Assembly on the grounds that membership in the Socialist Party constituted disloyalty to the United States. Although legally represented in the fight to retain his office by Charles Evans Hughes, a future United States Supreme Court Chief Justice, Claessens was denied his seat throughout the turbulent period of the Red Scare. In September 1920, Claessens was re-elected to the State Assembly in a special election, but again the anti-socialist forces, led by Assembly Speaker Thaddeus C. Sweet, refused to permit Claessens to take office. Finally, in 1922, Claessens was allowed to take office after being re-elected to the State Assembly for the third time.
In the mid-1930s Claessens withdrew from the Socialist Party and became the executive secretary and, later, the national chairman of the Social Democratic Federation. Claessens held the position of national chairman until his death in 1954. Besides his involvement with the Social Democratic Federation, Claessens also ran unsuccessfully for a number of local and state offices.
Claessens was one of the most active faculty members at the Rand School of Social Science. From the mid-1920s until his death in 1954, Claessens taught courses in such subject areas as public speaking, parliamentary procedure, psychology and social psychology, race relations, labor-management relations, socialist theory, contemporary politics, anthropology, and sex and society. Claessens also served as an instructor in several evening schools sponsored by various New York City labor unions. At these schools, Claessens primarily taught courses in public speaking and labor-management relations.
Scope and Content Note
The correspondence is arranged chronologically, the manuscript and lecture notes are arranged alphabetically, and the other series are arranged topically. Each series was assigned a capital letter for the purpose of serving as a frame number. In the following representative citation (XIV:C:13), the letter "C" stands for the 3rd series, and the number "13" for the 13th file therein, while the roman numeral indicates that the Claessens Papers are the 14th collection within the microfilm publication Socialist Collections in the Tamiment Library, 1872-1956.
The correspondence pertaining to August Claessens (XIV:A) and Hilda Claessens (XIV:B) contains little significant information. Several letters from Claessens emphasize the importance of humor in public speaking. other letters and telegrams contain information on socialist publications and activities, Claessens' 50th birthday and 25th year as a Socialist Party member, and other personal matters. Some of the prominent correspondents in these two series are Morris Hillquit, Otto Branstetter, Leo Steinke, Esther Friedman, Carl Sandburg, Charles Edward Russell, and Adolf A. Berle, Jr.
The largest series in this collection is the manuscript and lecture notes (XIV:C). This series, consisting of 78 subject files, includes manuscripts and notes of lectures, pamphlets, books, addresses, and statements. Each subject file within this series has been given a frame number and has been cited according to the title of the file in the complete reel list. In some instances, the titles of items within the subject file are cited in the complete reel list. of special interest in this series are Claessens' writings on socialist humor, particularly the rough draft of his book, Didn't We Have Fun?(XIV:C:13); a series of articles entitled, "Revolutionary Fun" (XIV:C:56); and a collection of anecdotes entitled, "We Struggled With a Smile" (XIV:C:73). This series also contains writings on human nature, prejudice, prohibition, contemporary politics, labor, socialism, heredity and environment, sex and society, and religion. A collection of seven poems (XIV:C:45), written by Claessens, are also included in this series.
The Claessens Papers also contain a series of 26 photographs (XIV:D). The photographs are arranged in chronological order and include portraits of August Claessens, group photographs, photographs of Claessens with other socialist figures, and photographs of Claessens teaching at the Rand School. Each photograph has been labeled with a number in the lower right-hand corner of the picture. These numbers correspond with the description of the photographs in the complete reel list. After being microfilmed, the photographs were separated to the Tamiment Library's photograph collection (see also: Separated Materials, below).
The printed matter in this collection (XIV:E) is organized into the following seven subject files: (1) Claessens legislative bills, New York State Assembly; (2) election campaigns; (3) lecture announcements; (4) miscellaneous; (5) pamphlets; (6) socialist legislative bills, New York State Assembly; and (7) testimonials. Each subject file has been assigned a frame number, including each item in the pamphlets file.
The legislative bills constitute the largest bulk of materials in the printed matter series. These bills are divided into two files: (1) 16 bills drafted by Claessens from 1918 to 1919 (XIV:E:1); and (2) 74 bills drafted by the five socialist assemblymen during the period, January-April 1918 (XIV:E:6). The bills which were drafted by Claessens have been described in the biographical sketch of this description. The bills drafted by the five socialist assemblymen include legislation on the regulation of municipal street railway fares, municipal ownership of public utilities, repeal of the state police department, abolishment of the death penalty, regulation of child labor, reorganization of the City College of New York, expansion of workmen's compensation, free university education, and the establishment of municipal day nurseries.
There are also five pamphlets in the printed matter series which were written by Claessens (XIV:E:5). These pamphlets are arranged in alphabetical order according to the title of the pamphlet. A bibliographical citation for each pamphlet in this file can be found in the complete reel list.
The last series consists of biographical clippings and published writings which were not microfilmed.
The researcher should note that an error was made in the targeting for this collection. on each frame the word "Series" appears adjacent to the frame number. This term should actually be interpreted as "Collection".
Arrangement
Arranged in six series: I. Correspondence, 1911-1955; II. Hilda Claessens Correspondence, 1915; III. Manuscript and Lecture Notes, 1906-1954; IV. Photographs, 1920-1936; V. Printed Matter, 1906-1953; VI. Biographical Clippings and Published Writings.
Folders are generally arranged alphabetically.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Socialist collections in the Tamiment Library, 1872-1956: a guide to the microfilm edition / edited by Thomas C. Pardo. Sanford, N.C.: Microfilming Corp. of America, c1979. 181 p.
Socialist Collections in the Tamiment Library, 1872-1956; includes: The Rand School of Social Science Records (Tamiment microfilm reel numbers: R2630-R2697)
Separated Material
August Claessens Photographs (collection number: Tamiment Photographs 69).
Berle, Adolf Augustus, 1895-1971.; Branstetter, Otto.; Friedman, Esther.; Hillquit, Morris, 1869-1933.; Rand School of Social Science.; Russell, Charles Edward, 1860-1941.; Sandburg, Carl, 1878-1967.; Social Democratic Federation of America.; Socialist Party (U.S.).; Steinke, Leo.; Articles.; Lectures.; Manuscripts for publication.; Pamphlets.; Photographic prints.; Socialism--United States.; Speeches.
- Series I. Correspondence, Feb 15, 1911-Aug 11, 1955
  - Correspondence, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General note
    Tamiment Reel number: R 2685 (Socialist Collections Reel 56) Frame XIV:A
  - Correspondence, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1913 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1927-1928 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1943-1944 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Series II. Hilda Claessens Correspondence
  - Correspondence, Jan 1915-Dec 31, 1915, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Tamiment Reel number: R 2685 (Socialist Collections Reel 56) Frame XIV: B
- Series III. Manuscript and Lecture Notes, 1906-1954, nd
  - ABC of Parliamentary Law, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Tamiment Reel number: R 2685 (Socialist Collections Reel 56) Frame XIV: C
  - Anthropology and the Growth of Society Contains 5 brief lectures: - The origin of Man and the Races of Mankind - Primitive Man and His World - The Savage and His Culture - The Barbarian and His World - Civilization, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - [Article on the 1932 campaign], 1933 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Can a Goy and a Yiddina Stay Happily Married?, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Changing Human Nature, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - The Chase for the Almighty Dollar, The End of the Chase, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Collective Bargaining, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Collectivism and Individual Liberty, Feb 1951 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Communism, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - The Cultural Elements, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Democracy vs. Dictatorship, Nov 1939, Jun-41 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Democratic Way of Life, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Didn't We Have Fun?, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Didn't We Have Fun?, undated (Box 2, Folder 13A)
  - Didn't We Have Fun?, undated (Box 2, Folder 13B)
  - Didn't We Have Fun?, undated (Box 2, Folder 13C)
  - Disagreeable and Dirty Work, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Einstein Theory, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Elementary and Advanced Socialism, Contains: Our Economic Chaos(3 copies) Lessons from the World War(2 copies) What Socialism Is(3 copies) The Distribution of Wealth(2 copies) The Love of Money The Odium of Menial Labor Instinct of Workmenship(2 copies) Incentive and Ambition(3 copies) Socialism and Ambition, 1930-1935, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Elements of Social Progress, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Ethics and Economics, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - The Evolution of Morality, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Florida Violence, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Genius, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Germany and Reparations, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Graft and Corruption, (4 copies), Mar 1932 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Guaranteed Annual Wage, undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Haiti, undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Heredity and Environment, Contains: Our Natural Heritage Our Natural Environment Nature and Nurture Problems of Physical Heritage Our Social Environment Our Social Heritage Problems of Social Heritage, 1931-1933, undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - If Lincoln Were Hoover, undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Immigration, undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Industrial Democracy, undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Is A United States of Europe Possible?, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Is Socialism Inevitable?, undated (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Is the Status of the Masses Improving?, Is the Condition of the Masses Growing Better or Worse?, undated, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - The Jew and the World Crisis, undated (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Justice Without A Blindfold, undated (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Labor Movement, undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Lectures on Behavior, Contains: The Instinctive Basis of Behavior Acquired Behavior - The Environmental Factors(2 copies) Social and Collective Behavior, 1940, undated (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - A Liberal Interlude(3 copies), undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Measures to Halt a Depression, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Modern Science, man, Religion and God, undated (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Must We Change Human Nature?, undated (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - The Nature of Work and the Nature of Man, undated (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - NRA(4 copies), Oct 1933 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Outlines and Highlights of the Social Sciences Biology Human Geography: The Cultural Backwardness of the South Psychology social Psychology-Prejudices and Stereotypes Anthropology, undated (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Patriotism, undated (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Poems, Contains: Remembrance(2 copies) On a Spring Greeting Card to Jennie(2 copies) Friendship Winter Enthusiasm The Months(2 copies) A Bit of Philosophy-Before Election, 1906-1920, undated (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Prejudices-A Story in Human Behavior, 1932-1943 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Prohibition, undated (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Promise of Socialism, undated (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Prosperity and Hard Times, Dec 1923 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Racketeers and Big Business, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Red Riots, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Relation of Work to Ignorance and Education, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Religion and Soviet Russia, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Resolution on African Independence, (2 copies), undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Resolution on Anti-Semitism, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Revolutionary Fun Contains: They Were All One to Him(2 copies) That Was the Purpose of the Meeting Obliging He Never Spoke on That Corner Again(2 copies) Got a Permit(3 copies) May Day Article Close Shave(2 copies) Kindly Suggestion(2 copies) Some Diet! It Can Happen Only in Harlem(2 copies) A Four Hour Day Hamlet Outdone Suggestively Ancient misses A Question in Physics Not an Encyclopedia Mathematics One on History One on the Professor One on the Teacher Biology as Franklin No Doubt Knew Three Humorous Bits: Phrenology an Englishman's Idea of American Humor Change of Nationality Mythology Materialism Versus Spiritualism, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - The Second industrial Revolution, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Sex and Society Contains: Women and Modern Industry Prostitution Marriage and Economics The Home-Present and Future The Home and Social Changes Marital Incompatibility Mental Differences of men and women(2 copies) Sex Prejudices, 1930-1935, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Social Attitudes Toward War and Peace(2 copies), 1936 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Social Psychology(4 copies), 1935-1938 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Socialism and Human Nature, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Socialism and Religion, undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Socialism and Social Problems, undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Socialism of George Bernard Shaw, undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Socialism in the Assembly, undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Stock Market, undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - These United States, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Unavoidable Hazard in Some Kinds of Work, undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Understanding the U.S.A., undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Understanding the Worker, undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - United Front, undated (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Wages and Prices, undated (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - We Struggled with a Smile Contains: An Innocent Deception(3 copies) On the Plains of Colorado(3 copies) Good Heavens!(3 copies) A British Prime Minister Meets His American Comrades(3 copies) I Work with a Notorious Racketeer Some Funny Moments in the Labor Movement The Germans in Our Midst The Benefits of Materialism(2 copies), undated (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - What Organized Labor Has Gained, undated (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - What Organized Labor Wants, undated (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - The Will to Live, undated (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Why They Threw Us Out of the Assembly, undated (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Notes, undated (Box 3, Folder 29)
- Series IV. Photographs, 1920-1936, nd
  Scope and Contents note
  Note: these items were separated from the collection after filming, and transferred to the Library's Photograph collection.
  - Photographs 1- 9. Portraits of August Claessens nd Photograph 10. Four of the five Assemblymen expelled by the New York State Assembly during the Red Scare. L-R: Charles Solomon, Louis Waldman, Samuel Orr, August Claessens ca. 1920 Photograph 11. Socialist agitators who toured the United States and spoke at Socialist meetings in many states, 1921. L-R, front: Isidore Goldstein and Norman Goldstein. L-R, rear: Sylvia Claessens, Hilda Claessens, August Claessens. ca. 1921 Photograph 12. August Claessens in his office at the headquarters of the Social Democratic Federation, New York City. 1935. Photograph 13. August Claessens, center in the second row, at an outing of the Young People's Socialist League. 1935. Photograph 14. August Claessens conducting a class in economics and public speaking at Local 62 of the International Ladies Garment Workers Union. 31 March 1936. Photograph 15. August Claessens speaking at an "Open Air" meeting in New York City. nd. Photograph 16. August Claessens speaking at an "Open Air" meeting and encouraging workers to read socialist publications. nd. Photograph 17. Part of a crowd attending a Socialist Party rally in New York City. nd. Photograph 18. August Claessens, center in the second row, with other Socialists and union members. nd. Photographs 19-21. August Claessens giving a lecture. nd. Photograph 22. August Claessens, far left, and one of his numerous Rand School classes nd. Photograph 23. August Claessens teaching a class in public speaking at the Rand School, January 1932. Photograph 24. August Claessens addressing a group of trade union representatives, nd. Photograph 25. August Claessens giving an address, nd. Photograph 26. August Claessens, center of the photograph, attending a dinner, nd., ca.1920-1940 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    Tamiment Reel number: R 2685 (Socialist Collections Reel 56) Frame XIV: D
- Series V. Printed Matter, 1909-1953, nd
  - Claessens Legislative Bills, New York State Assembly, 1918-1919 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    Tamiment Reel number: R 2685 (Socialist Collections Reel 56) Frame XIV: E
  - Election Campaigns, 1940, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Lecture Announcements, 1914-1953, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous, 1909-1922, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Pamphlets, Contains: 1. Claessens, August. The Blue Eagle Is Dead? So What! New York: New York Socialist Party, nd. l6pp. 2. Claessens, August. Is Socialism Inevitable? An Explanation of the Forces of Social Progress. Chicago: Socialist Party of the United States, 1922. 40pp. 3. Claessens, August. Roparska Trojica. Chicago: Jugoslovanska Delavska Tiskovna Druzoba, 1924. 63pp. 4. Claessens, August. The Trinity of Plunder. A Cheerful Slam at Rent, Interest, and Profit. New York: New York Call Printing Co., 1922. 32pp. 5. Claessens, August. Zasady Socjalizmu. Detroit: Wychodzi kazrdego.tygodnia, nd. 18pp., 1922-1924, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Socialist Legislative Bills, New York State Assembly, Jan 1918-Apr 1918 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Testimonials, Feb 13, 1928-Apr 22, 1950 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Duplicates of Microfilmed Items (I), undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
    Item not microfilmed
  - Duplicates of Microfilmed Items (II), undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Claessens Pamphlets A-E (I), 1930s-1940s (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Claessens Pamphlets A-E (II), 1930s-1940s (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Claessens Book Reviews, undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Claessens Newspapers Articles, Debates, etc., undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Claessens Articles, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - BF: Biographical File, undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - BF: Biographical File, 1912 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - BF: Biographical File, 1915 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - BF: Biographical File, 1919 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - BF: Biographical File, 1933 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - BF: Biographical File, 1934 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - BF: Biographical File, 1937 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - BF: Biographical File, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - BF: Biographical File, 1942 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - BF: Biographical File, 1944 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - BF: Biographical File, 1947 (Box 5, Folder 18)
- Biographical Clippings and Published Writings